<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gotdairyya blog</title>
    <description>Thoughts and musings about data vis, ethics, and everything else by derya akbaba.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Show Me The Money!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was co-written with Kiran and originally published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://vdl.sci.utah.edu/blog/2021/12/08/fair-pay-panel/&quot;&gt;VDL blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kirangadhave.me/&quot;&gt;Kiran&lt;/a&gt; and I co-organized a panel at IEEE VIS 2021 titled “Wait…when did we sign up to be economists?” The panel was moderated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://datascience.harvard.edu/people/carolina-nobre&quot;&gt;Carolina Nobre&lt;/a&gt;, and the panelists – &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.saiph.org&quot;&gt;Saiph Savage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://danielleszafir.com/&quot;&gt;Danielle Albers Szafir&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://vdl.sci.utah.edu/team/lex/&quot;&gt;Alexander Lex&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://steveharoz.com/&quot;&gt;Steve Haroz&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://khreda.com/&quot;&gt;Khairi Reda&lt;/a&gt; – were tasked with debating the ethics surrounding the decisions researchers make when determining the how much to pay crowdsourced study participants. The following article is a summary of the key points brought about by the panel. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/Qks3OA6vtH0&quot;&gt;recording of the panel&lt;/a&gt; is also available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we don’t know exactly how many papers submitted to IEEE VIS over the years used study participants, from anecdotal experience, it’s a lot. And during the pandemic, due to restrictions on in-person activities, such studies have moved online to crowdsourced platforms. This becomes problematic when research has shown that most crowdsourced workers make &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; less than minimum wage (about $3/hr on average &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, that can’t even buy you a cup of coffee these days).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the panel was two-fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(a) To bring awareness to the lack of guidelines for paying subjects fairly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(b) To begin outlining how to pay subjects fairly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the panel was only the beginning of what will (hopefully) be a series of conversations, here are some of the main points discussed, followed by some recommendations and resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-do-we-consider-fair-pay&quot;&gt;What Do We Consider Fair Pay?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no global standards which dictate fair wage, this results in participants in different regions getting paid differently. Even the discussion regarding what is fair is complicated – is fair pay a wage that supports some standard of living or is it a wage that meets some minimum wage standard? The problem is further exacerbated when we consider crowdsourced studies. The requester and the participants might be located all over the world. So how do we decide what a fair compensation is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting a high bar for payment might disadvantage less well-funded universities from participating in research. One of the suggestions that came up in the panel discussion was paying the minimum wage for the requester’s location. This approach does not address the problem of inequity between locations. A minimum wage from one location might be less than the minimum wage in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And simply setting a blanket-high wage runs into potential problems in a crowdsourcing environment, where the market wage is low. Paying significantly above market rate may be seen as undue influence or coercion. However, this is less of a harm than underpaying the workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need research to better understand workers, their expectations and the invisible labor that goes into crowd work. This will help us develop a more humane and compassionate pay scale. Meanwhile, as individual researchers we can take steps to better improve our compensation by thinking of crowdsourced workers as both workers and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;think-about-crowdsourced-workers-as-workers-and-people&quot;&gt;Think About Crowdsourced Workers as Workers and People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this statement sounds obvious, often the labor conditions of workers are not an explicit consideration of researchers; after all we are not managers, we are not responsible for their working conditions beyond our study, right? By taking a subtle shift in perspective, one focused on labor rights, the researcher becomes responsible for considering how their study impacts the working life of their participant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main themes that came up in the panel was a focus on transparency and fair working conditions. Paying attention to working conditions can include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being explicit and transparent to workers about what you expect the study conditions to entail&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being explicit and transparent to workers about what you are offering to pay them and why&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Factoring in bathroom breaks, life moments, etc. so that participants have ample time to complete a task without fear of losing compensation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-it-our-responsibility-to-think-about-this&quot;&gt;Is it Our Responsibility to Think about This?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the panel after all is “Wait…I never signed up to be an economist?” So why is the onus of fair pay placed on researchers? Why can’t we place the responsibility on research institutions responsible for reviewing experimental design, like the Institutional Review Board (IRB) or a publisher or professional organization sponsoring a conference, such as IEEE? At the moment, neither organizations enforce or have standards around fair pay. In some instances, the IRB will even flag that paying participants &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; may cause undue incentives in the experimental setup. Further, as outlined in Steve Haroz’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://steveharoz.com/blog/2021/the-unenumerated-rights-of-reviewers/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, the IEEE guidelines provide no mechanisms for raising ethical concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;enforcing-fair-pay&quot;&gt;Enforcing Fair Pay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panelists touched on three different avenues through which fair pay can be enforced: platforms, social media, and research communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Platform-based enforcements rely on technology to mediate the difference in expectations and behavior between crowdworkers and researchers. For example, by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://wagepledge.org&quot;&gt;Wage Pledge&lt;/a&gt;, workers are given avenues through which they can report researchers that do not deliver the payment or working conditions that were promised. Similarly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://prolific.co/&quot;&gt;Prolific&lt;/a&gt; mediates disputes between workers and researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another avenue of enforcement happens through social pressure. Subreddits and other messaging boards are used by workers to track and call out bad behavior when it comes to not paying people fairly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research community-based enforcement does not currently exist in visualization. We are hoping that this panel sets into motion more explicit action from our research community. This type of enforcement may look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting paper submission guidelines that ask researchers to specify participant compensation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a reviewer and paper chair, having the ability to reject or refuse to review research that chose to ignore ethical payment as part of their experimental considerations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is still so much to consider beyond this panel. Namely, there are discussions that can (and should) be had by organizing committees to formalize a set of guidelines for ethical pay in studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we wait, as researchers we can make the choice within our research to think about the ethical standards of our experiments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much are we paying individuals? Is this wage a living wage?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How will I pay participants that take longer to conduct the study?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have I articulated the working conditions I expect of the working conditions in my study? What avenues do workers have to communicate grievances or concerns?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, there is great work being done by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3449224&quot;&gt;Rivera et al.&lt;/a&gt; that proposes a design space for considering crowd-sourced tasks as opportunities to help workers develop employable skill sets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to a natural next question: Do we understand our crowdsourced worker’s wants and needs? Other fields like HCI and CSCW have explicitly explored this question. Should we collaborate with researchers in these fields to learn more or do we need to conduct our own studies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, this panel exposed that there is still more work that needs to be done as part of our responsibility to conduct research in an ethical manner. We’ve included a list of resources and tools below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://toloka.ai&quot;&gt;https://toloka.ai&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wagepledge.org&quot;&gt;https://wagepledge.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Papers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3476060&quot;&gt;On the invisible labor of crowdworkers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3173574.3174023?casa_token=S7GwvHoTGSoAAAAA%3AcwtoggH_Rz02vT7nMayWHvzqa7qokphcfMMNJWhb88cnSBsh3EwRni-BRLKD0Rb6UfceUQQtHcCn&quot;&gt;A review of crowdworker pay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3173574.3174023?casa_token=S7GwvHoTGSoAAAAA%3AcwtoggH_Rz02vT7nMayWHvzqa7qokphcfMMNJWhb88cnSBsh3EwRni-BRLKD0Rb6UfceUQQtHcCn&quot;&gt;The career goals of crowdworkers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/2702123.2702508&quot;&gt;Challenges to collective action for crowdsourced workers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;panelist-statements&quot;&gt;Panelist Statements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;!-- Saiph Savage --&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/654333114?h=6f905dc55a&amp;amp;badge=0&amp;amp;autopause=0&amp;amp;player_id=0&amp;amp;app_id=58479&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; title=&quot;saiph_statement&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;!-- Danielle Szafir --&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/654332674?h=46bceaeaaf&amp;amp;badge=0&amp;amp;autopause=0&amp;amp;player_id=0&amp;amp;app_id=58479&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; title=&quot;danielle_statement&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;!-- Alexander Lex --&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/654332529?h=7b28114615&amp;amp;badge=0&amp;amp;autopause=0&amp;amp;player_id=0&amp;amp;app_id=58479&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; title=&quot;alex_statement&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;!-- Khairi Reda --&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/654332896?h=44314403a8&amp;amp;badge=0&amp;amp;autopause=0&amp;amp;player_id=0&amp;amp;app_id=58479&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; title=&quot;khairi_statement&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;!-- Steve Haroz --&gt;
  &lt;div style=&quot;padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/654333299?h=ac0b0627aa&amp;amp;badge=0&amp;amp;autopause=0&amp;amp;player_id=0&amp;amp;app_id=58479&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;&quot; title=&quot;steve_statement&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;script src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Danielle Szafir, Steve Haroz, and Alex Lex for your edits!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hara, Kotaro, et al. “A data-driven analysis of workers’ earnings on Amazon Mechanical Turk.” Proceedings of the 2018 CHI conference on human factors in computing systems. 2018. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3173574.3174023?casa_token=S7GwvHoTGSoAAAAA%3AcwtoggH_Rz02vT7nMayWHvzqa7qokphcfMMNJWhb88cnSBsh3EwRni-BRLKD0Rb6UfceUQQtHcCn&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2021/12/08/fair-pay-panel.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2021/12/08/fair-pay-panel.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sorting Things Out</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you know a little about my past life (before pursuing a PhD, not in the karmic sense), you would know that I worked on a theory for economic classification systems. So it was no wonder that when &lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/sorting-things-out&quot;&gt;“Sorting things out: classification and its consequences”&lt;/a&gt; showed up on my goodreads, my old co-worker promptly commented “wow who are you!!!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would think 6 years embedded in discussions about classification systems would be enough for a lifetime…THINK AGAIN. I definitely had a moment where I felt incredulous picking up the book, but as soon as I started reading it, I knew I had made the right decision. This post is an attempt to capture some of the memorable aspects before they slip from my failing memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classification-systems-are-invisible-infrastructures&quot;&gt;Classification Systems are (invisible) Infrastructures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one major takeaway, it would be these:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;classification systems are often invisible&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;classification systems are powerful&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;classification systems are infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;invisibility&quot;&gt;Invisibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classification shapes the way that we think about the world and how we record that thought. Often, we do not think about how we are labeling the world around us (invisibility). We see an object and call it a flower. Or if we are a florist, we call it a peony. These examples are trivial, but in instances like classifying a disease, where many different causes might be at play, the choice in what and how to classify alters the types of treatment one may receive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;power&quot;&gt;Power&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In chapter 6 the authors discuss the very real ways in which classification of race during apartheid in South Africa affected people’s lives: limiting access to resources, dividing families, and numerous reclassifications. For a metaphysical discussion about race, please read “‘But What Are You Really?’ The Metaphysics of Race” by Charles Mills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;infrastructure&quot;&gt;Infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, classification systems as markers of community membership struck me as a super fascinating concept:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Categories are historically situated artifacts and, like all artifacts, are learned as part of membership in communities of practice.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They go on to discuss classification systems as boundary infrastructures, where classification systems serve as interpretable and flexible infrastructure on the edges of different communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we grapple with this all the time in my field (or any field that works with data). We assume that data means one thing and then quickly (if we are fortunate) find that it means something quite different to our collaborators. I think this is because as Johanna Drucker &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000091/000091.html&quot;&gt;states&lt;/a&gt; oh so eloquently, “&lt;em&gt;Data are capta&lt;/em&gt;, taken not given, constructed as an interpretation of the phenomenal world, not inherent in it.” The act of creating data is an act of classification: what is classified, who classifies, why classified…This is is a thread in feminist data visualization that I think deserves more discussion, but I feel the limitations of that discussion because we are just flooded with data every second of every day. Where can we find the time to pause and examine the construction of data? When can we refuse data as given? A thread to be continued elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-opportunities&quot;&gt;Design Opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last two pages of the book, the authors provide recommendations for how to design classification systems. &lt;em&gt;Why only two pages?&lt;/em&gt; I summarize the recommendations here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Having “grey area” in classification systems is a good thing.&lt;/strong&gt; It provides space and flexibility for using these systems across different contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep the people who designed the systems visible.&lt;/strong&gt; This will hopefully prevent the system from becoming invisible and as such assumed as natural and a given.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be aware of what/who falls into other categories.&lt;/strong&gt; Essentially, anyone or thing not specifically classified becomes lost in the archive, blending with everything else placed in the other category. There are mixed reactions to this in current feminist and queer literature. For example, “Becoming NULL: Queer relations in the excluded middle” by Jacob Gaboury, advocates that using the NULL category is a subversive act that reduces the effectiveness of data (specifically in the context of surveillance). While in “Uncertain Archives: Approaching the Unknowns, Errors, and Vulnerabilities of Big Data through Cultural Theories of the Archive,” Agostinho et al. discuss the tension between exclusion from archival data, an erasure from history, and increasing surveillance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, while many of us tend to use data and are critical of it to some extent, a discussion may be worth having of the content of the classification system… where it came from and how does it frame the way we consider the phenomena at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2021/06/09/sorting-things-out.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2021/06/09/sorting-things-out.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meta-confused about Metacognition</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As the (slightly modified for personal taste) proverb goes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Give a girl a tofu sandwich and she is full for a day. Teach that girl how to cook the tofu sandwhich, and she is full for many days (until she gets sick of said sandwhich).”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teaching someone &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do something is better than just doing it for them. Extended to learning, teaching someone how to learn means that they can keep learning new content on their own. This awareness of how you learn is often referred to as metacognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems simple enough right? Well it is actually a real head scratcher (for me at least). I’ll start off with some formal definitions of metacognition and then discuss some of the difficulties with teaching students metacognitive strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is part of my summer CS Education Research (CSER) series. All summer I am co-moderating a CSER reading group and will be using these blog posts to summarize discussions and thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s post mainly draws from a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3372782.3406263&quot;&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt; by Prather et al. titled: “What Do We Think We Think We Are Doing?: Metacognition and Self-Regulation in Programming.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metacognition&quot;&gt;Metacognition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As defined by Prather et al.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metacognition&lt;/strong&gt; tends to be the term used to describe knowledge about one’s own cognitive control, including identifying strategies that have been successful or unsuccessful in the past, monitoring emotions and self-efficacy, and evaluating the validity of metacognitive knowledge based on feed-back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So metacognition is an awareness of ways in which you have learned in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When applying metacognition to the problem at hand, the term is called self-regulation. Again, Prather et al.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…self-regulation tends to be the term used to describe the process of executing cognitive control during a learning or problem-solving task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these terms are forms of cognitive control. Why am I introducing all these terms? Well, for me, I had only heard of metacognition and the introduction of self-regulation into my lexicon really helped distinguish metacognition prior-/post- learning and metacognition during-learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/metacognition.png&quot; alt=&quot;diagram of how I mentally relate metacognition and self-regulation&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And like all nebulous concepts about how the mind works, there are different theories that highlight different aspects of the phenomenon. In our reading group, we had trouble deeply connecting with any of the theories presented in the paper, but recognized the value of having them all in one place for future use in experimental set-ups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major issue with understanding metacognition is that it is an internal process and thus hard to measure. The paper reviews both instruments for measuring metacognition and tools to help students grow their metacognition. Sounds great right? The problem is that there are mixed results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3372782.3406257&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; outside of the study, “Exploring Student Behavior Using the TIPP&amp;amp;SEE Learning Strategy,” the authors used scaffolding methods to aid students in metacognitive thinking before working on a problem. While the technique helped students for the given problem, the researchers could not confirm that it supported development of metacognitive abilities. &lt;em&gt;What gives?&lt;/em&gt; Seems like teaching and learning are difficult, who would’ve thunk? :upside_down_face: An insightful comment made by a fellow reading group participant was that there seems to be an element of practice that is relevant for learning about metacognition. Leaving teachers and researchers where? That more practice with explicit metacognitive strategies might stick if they are practiced enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is where I will leave you, my fellow reader. I hope you’re not as meta-confused as I am about cognitive control. If you come across more readings please &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gotdairyya&quot;&gt;tweet&lt;/a&gt; at me, I would love to discuss!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2021/06/03/getting-meta-about-metacognition.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2021/06/03/getting-meta-about-metacognition.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cooking Up Knowledge</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I have always been fascinated with how we come to know things. Not just from a memorization perspective (in fact, I remember what I once memorized, but can no longer recall the content, which makes me question &lt;em&gt;the point&lt;/em&gt;), but rather from an embodied perspective. When do our muscles remember how to ride a bike? or our taste buds recommend the tiniest bit of lemon juice to balance the flavors? The inspiration for this post came when I was exchanging Turkish recipes&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with a friend, who was in turn exchanging Bangladeshi recipes. In addition to the recipe, we both included long explanations of what needed to be done so that the recipe would turn out like the way our grand-/mothers made the recipe (aka the right way). The ancesteral, cultural, and gustatory knowledge was embedded in the practice of cooking, eating and family; and yet, mostly missing from the black and white text of the recipes. We attempted to fill in this gap with more text, but it is unclear either of us will make the dishes authentically. This exchange reminded me about two academic concepts that I have been fascinated with as of late: tacit knowledge in science and pedagogical content knowledge in education. Both relate to how &lt;em&gt;verbs&lt;/em&gt; are done and the quality to which they are done. Below I include a BRIEF overview of each. I am still new to both fields/concepts, and so I would love further recommendations and to engage in more discussion (just tweet &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gotdairyya&quot;&gt;@gotdairyya&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the social studies of science, tacit knowledge has been studied as the magic sauce for getting science done. In H.M. Collins’ Paper,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; he discusses how tacit knowledge plays an important role in measuring the quality of sapphire. &lt;em&gt;A brief aside, the shortening of the quality of sapphire is the q of sapphire and that always conjures up for me images of Quailman.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;https://media.giphy.com/media/l4EpkQcjHPsr9tTP2/giphy.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Quailman an early 2000s cartoon character&quot; class=&quot;scale-50-center&quot; /&gt; It is a super fascinating read discussing how the lingering dynamics of Cold War politics were overcome over by two labs spending time together, learning the way experiments were conducted through engaging in observation and learning, ultimately united by ‘the language of science.’ If this isn’t a thriller, I don’t know what is. To read more, I would recommend the works of Susan Leigh Star and Geoffrey Bowker. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In education research, I’ve seen tacit knowledge show up as Pedagogical Content Knowledge (PCK). PCK “encapsulates all that the teacher has to know in order to teach a subject effectively”. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Effectively could mean how to get the students excited about the topic, how to teach so that students can recall concepts in later and differing concepts, what metaphors tend to work and which ones don’t, teaching inclusive design &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;…There is so much to the act of teaching that extends beyond the content material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have written about is just scratching the surface of the different ways of knowing. I wanted to jot down these inital thoughts, fully recognizing that they are incomplete. From cooking, to social studies of science, to education research knowing about knowing + knowing about doing impact the types of things that can be done and the extent to which they can be done well. How often are we engaging in discussions at this meta-level?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What fascinates me is how can we communicate all the stuff we know about stuff? Are there ways to hint at how little the instructions we write or the data we display represent the full and embodied nature of our knowing? How can technological systems support/obstruct the transfer of knowledge?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acknowledgements&quot;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I need to thank Os Keyes for bringing all of the tacit knowledge papers to my attention and Eliane Wiese for the papers on PCKs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[1]&lt;/strong&gt; Here is my recipe for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1YSAiKWlD3YjaoIJhVheg7uDbISUI9edG9rAxSuDwbP0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;vegan spinach borek&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[2]&lt;/strong&gt; Collins, H. M. (2001). Tacit knowledge, trust and the Q of Sapphire. Social Studies of Science, 31(1), 71–85. https://doi.org/10.1177/030631201031001004 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[3]&lt;/strong&gt; Bowker, G. C., &amp;amp; Star, S. L. (1999). Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences. Massachusetts Institute of Technology. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[4]&lt;/strong&gt; Brandes, O., &amp;amp; Armoni, M. (2019). Using action research to distill research-based segments of pedagogical content knowledge of K-12 computer science teachers. Annual Conference on Innovation and Technology in Computer Science Education, ITiCSE, 485–491. https://doi.org/10.1145/3304221.3319773 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[5]&lt;/strong&gt; Oleson, A., Mendez, C., Steine-Hanson, Z., Hilderbrand, C., Perdriau, C., Burnett, M., &amp;amp; Ko, A. J. (2018). Pedagogical content knowledge for teaching inclusive design. ICER 2018 - Proceedings of the 2018 ACM Conference on International Computing Education Research, 69–77. https://doi.org/10.1145/3230977.3230998 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2021/04/18/cooking-knowledge.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2021/04/18/cooking-knowledge.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is Data Vis?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I often get asked – what is data vis? And often I answer with: “Well, it’s visualizing data. “ Incredibly helpful. I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, inspired by the very unhelpful patent images of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://noahveltman.com/internet-shape/&quot;&gt;shape of the internet&lt;/a&gt; found by Noah Veltman, I have found equally unhelpful images of data visualizations. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;strange white man from the 50s reads tablet&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://patents.google.com/patent/US20150220607A1/en?q=data+visualization&amp;amp;oq=data+visualization&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-vis/contextual-vis.png&quot; alt=&quot;strange white man from the 50s&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cute screens talk business to one another&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://patents.google.com/patent/US6995768B2/en?q=data+visualization&amp;amp;oq=data+visualization&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-vis/business-vis.png&quot; alt=&quot;cute screens talk business to one another&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;vis can make you smile&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://patents.google.com/patent/US20170262425A1/en?q=data+visualization&amp;amp;oq=data+visualization&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-vis/smiley-vis.png&quot; alt=&quot;vis can make you smile&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;aol man gets webcam&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://patents.google.com/patent/US20180189990A1/en?q=data+visualization&amp;amp;oq=data+visualization&amp;amp;page=1&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-vis/aol-vis.png&quot; alt=&quot;aol man gets webcam&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/11/27/what-is-datavis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/11/27/what-is-datavis.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Communicating Science Research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In early July I was a participant in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://comscicon.com/&quot;&gt;ComSciCon Flagship workshop&lt;/a&gt;. The 3-day workshop was conducted over Zoom and covered a variety of topics on how to communicate science research with non-scientists (we are all scientists but some of us choose to pursue it as a career). We discussed topics like empathy, complicating the narrative, heard from speakers on IDEA (Inclusion, Diversity, Equity, and Accessibility), and did a little improv to practice discomfort and thinking on our feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the conference, we were required to write a pop-science piece and then submit it to different journals. My piece was accepted by &lt;em&gt;Natural History&lt;/em&gt; and published in the September 2020 issue along with other ComSciCon participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing that I want to stress from this experience is that COMPUTER SCIENCE NEEDS MORE POP SCIENCE WRITERS!!!!! The Natural Sciences have it DOWN. But why let them have all the fun? Computers are in our daily lives, in our pockets, mediating the world we live in, and we (not the royal we, but the we-as-a-society we) would greatly benefit from a larger collective understanding about what computers are, what they do, and what research is being conducted about them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IF YOU ARE A COMPUTER SCIENTIST READING THIS, LET’S TALK!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was a wonderful experience working with an editor (thank you for all of the comments and feedback!). I’ve listed resources on how to pitch to an editor below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read the piece by buying the magazine, or &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/nh/Sep20-NH-digital-edition.pdf&quot;&gt;here is my digital copy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/nh/nh-cover.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of the cover of the September 20 magazine. An adorable bat!&quot; class=&quot;scale-50-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Pitch to an Editor:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/business/archive/2013/08/how-not-to-pitch/279193/&quot;&gt;the Atlantic’s ‘How (Not) to Pitch’&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theopennotebook.com/pitch-database/&quot;&gt;the Open Notebook’s Pitch Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@annfriedman/how-and-where-to-pitch-your-writing-1c316fa37bda&quot;&gt;Medium article on how to make a pitch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/09/10/comscicon.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/09/10/comscicon.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Perspective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Came across this image on perspective: I’ve tried to figure out the illustrator + origin, but both Google and Pinterest failed me. (For all I know, the poster could be about something completely different, so if you have any leads on it please let me know!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely ignorant about the text, the colors and simplicity really struck me and I decided to play around a little with the background image. Yes, there is probably some deep meaning about the images I chose (like cows representing veganism and mountains representing the humbling power of nature), but ultimately the decisions were based on colors and composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/perspective/perspective-OG.png&quot; alt=&quot;original image on perspective displaying a pink tent 2-d image. There are three eyes that point out the different way this flattened three dimensional image can be interpreted: a square from one side, a triangle from the other, and two rectangles from the top.&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/perspective/perspective-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;my copy of the original because the original is a picture of an image.&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/perspective/perspective-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;my copy of the original with a cow in the background&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/perspective/perspective-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;my copy of the original with mountains and a beautiful Utah sunset in the background&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/08/15/perspective.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/08/15/perspective.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning about Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s in many ways unbelievable to me that my first academic year of my PhD has come to an end. Not that I didn’t think I would make it, but more so I could not have even imagined the state of the world as it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global pandemic has affected all of our lives sounds like an understatement. I take a few moments each day while I am slightly panicked or overwhelmed to pause and pretend how in a few years from now I will be looking back and recounting all the disruptions and things that I have learned in this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is it that I have learned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(1) Don’t take anything for granted.&lt;/strong&gt;
This includes the little things like going to the grocery store after 8pm. And the big things, like cherishing the time you spend with friends and family.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(2) Video calls are awesome.&lt;/strong&gt;
I think after this has passed I will continue to video call my friends and family. Video calling has helped me to pause and remain present during phone calls, when in the past I viewed calls as something to do while I was doing other things. I have come to love quick little updates from my family. Even the long video calls with my sister as we walk around our neighborhoods, East Bench and the Bronx, talking about nothing and everything at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(3) Everything takes time.&lt;/strong&gt;
In some ways this year was harder than I imagined it would be. On and off I was plagued with imposter syndrome, worried that I was not doing research right. And I’m not sure when this happened, but towards the end of the semester something clicked for me – all of this is just going to take time and practice. In the same way that I have been learning how to enjoy the act of running, I am learning how to be a PhD student. There is definitely something meta here like “it’s not about the destination, it’s about the journey” and sure that totally applies, but no one mentioned the liberation you can feel when you begin to embrace that mindset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(4) Epistemology is not an onomatopoeia for a sneeze.&lt;/strong&gt; In fact, it is a super useful term to have in your toolbox and can help explain why you may disagree with someone else’s conclusions. I plan on writing an entry about this soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t necessarily have a good conclusion for this entry because I am in a state of learning and processing but I have been accepted to &lt;a href=&quot;https://comscicon.com/&quot;&gt;ComSciCon&lt;/a&gt; and I hope that through the weekend virtual workshop I will have some new methods of communicating to experiment with!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update Sept 9,2020: Read more about my experience with ComSciCon &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/09/10/comscicon.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/05/01/learning-about-learning.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/05/01/learning-about-learning.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Trustworthiness in Qualitative Research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I am taking a class taught by my advisor Miriah Meyer on ontologies, epistemologies, and research paradigms. I will have to write another post on what those words mean at some point, but for now I want to focus on an interesting conversation we have been having: how can researchers communicate rigor if their work is qualitative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-to-trust-a-positivist-perspective&quot;&gt;Learning to Trust: a Positivist Perspective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Positivism is a research paradigm often associated with the natural sciences. In the world of positivism, there are objective and generalizable truths that can be measured. Within positivism, research results are judged according to the following criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal Validity:&lt;/strong&gt; how certain are you that the independent variable has effected the dependent variable?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Validity:&lt;/strong&gt; how representative is the sample population (and by extension your results) of the general population?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducibility &amp;amp; Reliability:&lt;/strong&gt; how likely are the results to show up again in another experiment? how well can another researcher run your experiment?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectivity:&lt;/strong&gt; are the measurements value free?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These criteria are often associated with quantitative studies, but they become problematic when there is no &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; answer to your research, no &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; singular truth, and when the socio-, historical-, political- contexts of the experiment can greatly affect your results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter, Lincoln, Guba, and interpretivism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;establishing-trustworthiness&quot;&gt;Establishing Trustworthiness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following section is my take on organizing the work presented in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethnographyworkshop.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/lincoln-guba-1985-establishing-trustworthiness-naturalistic-inquiry.pdf&quot;&gt;Establishing Trustworthiness&lt;/a&gt;. Written in 1985, this document from my understanding is a seminal piece in interpretivist research methods. Lincoln and Guba set out to both make a case for interpretivism (the research paradigm that multiple realities exist and it is the role of the researcher to interpret it) and provide practical methods for establishing trust and rigor in qualitative research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credibility:&lt;/strong&gt; How congruent are the findings with reality? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Positivist Analogy: internal validity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Methods&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adopting appropriate research methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Establishing a rapport with the participants through long-term engagement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expanding participants to include randomly selected individuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyzing edge cases and how they fit or don&apos;t fit within your research conclusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Debriefing with peers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking your conclusions with the research participants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triangulating results using different sources of deta, methods of collection, and interpretations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transferability:&lt;/strong&gt; To what extent are the findings applicable to other contexts? It is important to note that the onus of transferring research results falls on the consumer of the research.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Positivist Analogy: external validity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Methods&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using thick descriptions to communicate the context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Including information regarding the type of data used (or omitted), length of study, participants, and other relevant details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dependability:&lt;/strong&gt; Have you provided enough information so that other researchers could repeat the work? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Positivist Analogy: reproducibility &amp;amp; reliability&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Methods&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Explaining the research design in rich details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enumerating the methods of gathering data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reflexive journaling&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confirmability:&lt;/strong&gt; Does your data support your interpretations? &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Positivist Analogy: objectivity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Methods&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Including an audit trail for review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintaining transparency about your methods, research design, and conclusion development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, even with these methods, it is hard to grapple with what makes research trustworthy? Especially in a non-positivist paradigm we are relying on individual interpretations, where there will not be one single correct answer. For me, this is the beauty of science that is often overlooked: as humans we have the innate ability to observe the world around us and communicate our observations with others to build collective knowledge, knowing that we may not be 100% correct all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Further Reading:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ792970&quot;&gt;More in depth methods summarized from the Lincoln and Guba paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2020/01/22/trustworthiness.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2020/01/22/trustworthiness.html</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Data Portraits</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I started writing this blog post a couple times, not entirely sure what was the appropriate introduction to a topic I am deeply fascinated with, so here are a few intros that didn’t make the cut…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instead of working on my final project for data vis, I am writing about it…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Really if you think about it, everything is a data portrait…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If everything is a data portrait, then what is a data portrait?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, not the best intros. What I would like to do instead, is talk about some inspiration I’ve had over the years regarding data portraits, and then show you what I have created for a class project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inspiration-comes-in-many-forms&quot;&gt;Inspiration Comes in Many Forms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One form is Georgia Lupi. Lupi a partner at Pentagram studios and a long time advocate for &lt;em&gt;data humanism&lt;/em&gt;, constantly likes to remind us that data is never the point, the humans who created it are. I hope to draw on this concept throughout my PhD. Often, data is assumed to be objective, immutable, authoritative, but ultimately it is another human creation, prone to errors and up to interpretation.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/giorgia_lupi_how_we_can_find_ourselves_in_data?language=en#t-258497&quot;&gt;For more on Lupi, you can listen to her TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/georgia-lupi-portraits.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;example of data portraits from Georgia Lupi&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An example of data portraits courtesy of ideas.ted.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another inspiration comes from nature and ways in which data can be interpreted as traces and proof of life. In Dietmar Offenhuber’s paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.05454&quot;&gt;Data by Proxy&lt;/a&gt;, he discusses the concept of discovering and revealing the traces of natural processes and abstracting them into a data and data visualizations. Although it might sound slightly abstract, I think it is something we do rather intuitively…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see patterns in how we step by looking at the uneven wear on the soles of our shoes.
The rings of trees show us the age of the tree.
White and grey hairs indicate age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want, we can take all these observations and abstract them into numbers, but maybe I will talk about that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final, but not final, inspiration comes from an Italian data visualization designer, Federica Fragapane, who makes the most out-of-this-world data portraits. I’ll let the examples below speak for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/federica-fragapane-carbon-dioxide.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;example of data portraits from Federica Fragapane&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/federica-fragapane-violent-cities.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;example of data portraits from Federica Fragapane&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You can find more of her work on her &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.behance.net/FedericaFragapane&quot;&gt;Behance site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-take-of-data-portraits&quot;&gt;My take of Data Portraits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my group project, we are visualizing data about museum artifacts. In spirit of the artwork, I wanted to create art that would represent the museum and it’s collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began by looking at different Abstract Expressionism art, looking specifically for the use of bold colors and geometric shapes. Once I selected an artist for inspiration, I created a rough mockup using pen + paper of what the portrait could look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/portrait-mockup.png&quot; alt=&quot;data portrait mock-up on post-it note&quot; class=&quot;scale-50-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pleased with the rough sketch, I used Adobe Illustrator for cleaner mock-ups. After implementing the design in code using fake (but representative) data, I altered the design slightly to both make the coding easier and incorporate a more organic element into the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/data-portrait-mockup-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;data portrait mock-up from illustrator&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/data-portrait-mockup-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;data portrait mock-up from illustrator&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/data-portrait-mockup-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;data portrait mock-up from illustrator&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/../assets/images/data-portraits/data-portrait-mockup-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;data portrait mock-up from illustrator&quot; class=&quot;responsive-image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is an interactive version of the portraits: &lt;br /&gt;
Hover to see the museum each portrait represents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;html lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
  &lt;meta charset=&quot;utf-8&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;meta name=&quot;viewport&quot; content=&quot;width=device-width, initial-scale=1&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;script src=&quot;https://d3js.org/d3.v5.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
  .porButton {
    fill: rgba(255, 225, 225, 0);
  }

  .porButton.not-selected {
    fill: rgba(255, 225, 225, .5);
  }

  .porButton.selected {
    fill: rgba(255, 225, 225, 0);
  }

  .porButton:hover {
    fill: rgba(255, 225, 225, 0)
  }

  .porButton:not(hover) {
    fill: rgba(255, 225, 225, .5);
  }

  div.tooltip {
    /* FOR PORTRAIT TOOLTIP */
    position: absolute;
    text-align: center;
    width: 60px;
    height: 28px;
    padding: 2px;
    font: 12px sans-serif;
    background: lightsteelblue;
    border: 0px;
    border-radius: 8px;
    pointer-events: none;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;body&gt;
  &lt;script&gt;
    let data = [{
        museum: &quot;canada-science-and-technology-museums&quot;,
        years: 26970,
        countries: 59,
        artifacts: 26970,
        yearWidths: [0, 0, 0, 0, 1]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;cleveland-museum-of-art&quot;,
        years: 43957,
        countries: 84,
        artifacts: 43957,
        yearWidths: [0.0027754396341879563, 0.033669267693427665, 0.03269103896990241, 0.10021157039834383, 0.8306526833041381]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;cooper-hewitt-smithsonian-design-museum&quot;,
        years: 20117,
        countries: 69,
        artifacts: 20117,
        yearWidths: [0, 0.4706467167072625, 0.00004970920117313715, 0.0005965104140776457, 0.5287070636774867]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;metropolitan-museum-of-art&quot;,
        years: 67113,
        countries: 160,
        artifacts: 67113,
        yearWidths: [0.4162531849269143, 0.05827484988005305, 0.09899721365458257, 0.08943125772950099, 0.3370434938089491]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;museum-of-modern-art&quot;,
        years: 70716,
        countries: 102,
        artifacts: 70716,
        yearWidths: [0, 0, 0, 0, 1]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;penn-museum&quot;,
        years: 43518,
        countries: 103,
        artifacts: 43518,
        yearWidths: [0.542005606875316, 0.15290224734592583, 0.04051197205753941, 0.03531871869111632, 0.22926145503010248]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;minneapolis-institute-of-art&quot;,
        years: 9906,
        countries: 20,
        artifacts: 9906,
        yearWidths: [0, 0, 0, 0.0031294165152432867, 0.9968705834847568]
      },
      {
        museum: &quot;global&quot;,
        years: 2,
        countries: 1,
        artifacts: 2,
        yearWidths: [0, 1, 0, 0, 0]
      }
    ]


    let artifactsNum = []
    for (let museum of data) {
      artifactsNum.push(museum.artifacts)
    }

    let i = 0;
    let svg = d3.select(&quot;div.article-entry&quot;).append(&quot;svg&quot;).attr(&quot;width&quot;, 500).attr(&quot;height&quot;, 600)
    for (let museum of data) {
      drawPortrait(museum, i, svg)
      i++
    }


    function drawPortrait(museum, i, svg) {
      // let svg = d3.select(&quot;div.article-entry&quot;).append(&quot;svg&quot;).attr(&quot;width&quot;, 500).attr(&quot;height&quot;, 600)
      svg = svg.append(&quot;g&quot;)

      let colors = [&quot;#b5a5e3&quot;, &quot;#b1af00&quot;, &quot;#ff5b1a&quot;, &quot;#e2a333&quot;, &quot;#5b7769&quot;]

      let artifactScale = d3.scaleOrdinal()
        .domain([d3.min(artifactsNum), d3.max(artifactsNum)])
        .range([1, 5])

      let frameWidth = 238 * .3
      let frameHeight = 360 * .3
      let rectWidth = [0]

      let portraitColors = svg
        .selectAll(&quot;rect&quot;)
        .data(museum.yearWidths)
        .join(&quot;rect&quot;)
        .attr(&quot;height&quot;, frameHeight)
        .attr(&quot;width&quot;, (d, i) =&gt; {
          rectWidth.push((d * frameWidth) + rectWidth[i]);
          return d * frameWidth
        })
        .style(&quot;fill&quot;, (d, i) =&gt; colors[i])
        .attr(&quot;x&quot;, (d, i) =&gt; rectWidth[i])
        .attr(&quot;transform&quot;, &quot;translate(7,5)&quot;)

      let lineWidth = artifactScale(museum.artifacts)

      let artifactLine = svg
        .append(&quot;line&quot;)
        .attr(&quot;x1&quot;, frameWidth / 2)
        .attr(&quot;y1&quot;, frameHeight)
        .attr(&quot;x2&quot;, frameWidth)
        .attr(&quot;y2&quot;, frameHeight - (frameWidth / 2))
        .style(&quot;stroke&quot;, &quot;black&quot;)
        .style(&quot;stroke-width&quot;, lineWidth)
        .attr(&quot;transform&quot;, &quot;translate(5,5)&quot;)

      let countries = museum.countries
      countries = countries / 6;
      countries = Math.round(countries)
      let countryArray = []

      for (let i = 0; i &lt; countries; i++) {
        countryArray.push(i)
      }

      let countryDots = svg
        .selectAll(&quot;circle&quot;)
        .data(countryArray)
        .join(&quot;circle&quot;)

      let j = 0;
      let k = 3
      countryDots
        .attr(&quot;r&quot;, 5)
        .attr(&quot;cx&quot;, function(d, i) {
          if (i &lt; 10) {
            if (i % 2 === 0) {
              return (i * 10) + 10
            } else {
              return (i * 10) + 20
            }
          } else if (i &gt;= 10 &amp;&amp; i &lt; 20) {
            if (i % 2 === 0) {
              j = j + 1
              return (j * 10) + 10
            } else {
              j = j + 1
              return (j * 10) + 20
            }
          } else {
            if (i % 2 === 0) {
              k = k + 1
              return (k * 10) + 10
            } else {
              k = k + 1
              return (k * 10)
            }
          }
        })
        .attr(&quot;cy&quot;, function(d, i) {
          if (i &lt; 10) {
            return (i * 10) + 10
          } else if (i &gt;= 10 &amp;&amp; i &lt; 20) {
            return ((i - 10) * 10) + 10
          } else {
            return ((i - 20) * 10 - 10)
          }
        })
        .attr(&quot;transform&quot;, &quot;translate(7,20) scale(.5)&quot;)

      let ticker = i
      svg
        .attr(&quot;transform&quot;, function() {
          if (ticker &lt; 4) {
            if (ticker === 0) {
              return `translate(0,${frameHeight*.2})`
            } else {
              return `translate(0,${ticker*1.2*frameHeight+(frameHeight*.2)})`
            }
          } else {
            ticker = ticker - 4
            if (ticker === 0) {
              return `translate(${frameWidth*1.2},${frameHeight*.2})`
            } else {
              return `translate(${frameWidth*1.2},${ticker*1.2*frameHeight+(frameHeight*.2)})`
            }
          }
        })
        .attr(&quot;margin&quot;, 20)

      let frame = svg.append(&quot;rect&quot;)
        .attr(&quot;width&quot;, frameWidth)
        .attr(&quot;border&quot;, 20)
        .attr(&quot;height&quot;, frameHeight)
        .style(&quot;stroke&quot;, &quot;black&quot;)
        .style(&quot;stroke-width&quot;, 5)
        // .style(&quot;fill&quot;, &quot;none&quot;)
        // .style(&quot;fill&quot;, &quot;rgba(35, 29, 150, 0)&quot;)
        .attr(&quot;transform&quot;, &quot;translate(5,5)&quot;)
        .attr(&quot;id&quot;, museum.museum)
        .attr(&quot;class&quot;, &quot;porButton&quot;)
      // .attr(&quot;data-tabindex&quot;, 0)


      frame.on(&quot;mouseover&quot;, function(d) {
        let title = museum.museum
        // d3.selectAll(&quot;.porButton&quot;).attr(&quot;opacity&quot;, title === that.vizCoord.activeMuseum ? 1 : .2)
        title === &quot;metropolitan-museum-of-art&quot; ? title = &quot;The Met&quot; : title === &quot;minneapolis-institute-of-art&quot; ? title = &quot;Mia&quot; : title === &quot;cooper-hewitt-smithsonian-design-museum&quot; ? title = &quot;Cooper Hewitt&quot; : title === &quot;penn-museum&quot; ? title =
          &quot;Penn Museum&quot; : title === &quot;cleveland-museum-of-art&quot; ? title = &quot;Cleveland Museum of Art&quot; : title === &quot;museum-of-modern-art&quot; ? title = &quot;MoMa&quot; : title === &quot;global&quot; ? title = &quot;All Museums&quot; : title =
          &quot;Canada Science and Technology Museum&quot;
        d3.select(this).append(&apos;svg:title&apos;)
          .text(title)
      });


    } //end drawPortraits

    // make responsive
    // resizeSVG(svg) {
    //   let that = this
    //   // get container + svg aspect ratio
    //   let container = d3.select(svg.node().parentNode),
    //     width = parseInt(svg.style(&quot;width&quot;)),
    //     height = parseInt(svg.style(&quot;height&quot;)),
    //     aspect = width / height;
    //
    //   svg.attr(&quot;viewBox&quot;, &quot;0 0 &quot; + width + &quot; &quot; + height)
    //     .attr(&quot;perserveAspectRatio&quot;, &quot;xMinYMid&quot;)
    //     .call(resize);
    //
    //   d3.select(window).on(&quot;resize.&quot; + container.attr(&quot;id&quot;), resize);
    //
    //   // get width of container and resize svg to fit it
    //   function resize() {
    //     let targetWidth = parseInt(container.style(&quot;width&quot;));
    //     svg.attr(&quot;width&quot;, targetWidth);
    //     svg.attr(&quot;height&quot;, Math.round(targetWidth / aspect));
    //   }
    // }
  &lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000//2019/11/21/data-portraits.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000//2019/11/21/data-portraits.html</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>